I want you to put off your preconceptions,
أريد منكم أن [تنقوا رؤوسكم] من الأفكار المسبقة الخاصة بكم،
your preconceived fears and thoughts about reptiles.
الخاصة بالمخاوف والأفكار المسبقة حول الزواحف.
Because that is the only way I'm going to get my story across to you.
لأن ذلك هو السبيل الوحيد لأحكي لكم قصتي
And by the way, if I come across as a sort of
وبالمناسبة، إذا كنت تأتي كنوع من
rabid, hippie conservationist,
الافكار المسعورة المخيفة والمتناقضة
it's purely a figment of your imagination.
فانها محض نسج من الخيال الخاص بك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay. We are actually the first species on Earth
حسنا. ونحن في الواقع فعليا أول الأنواع على الأرض
to be so prolific to actually threaten our own survival.
واننا النوع الوحيد الذي يهدد بقائه
And I know we've all seen images enough to make us numb,
وأنا أعلم أننا رأينا مايكفي من الصور لتجعلنا مخدرين
of the tragedies that we're perpetrating on the planet.
من المآسي التي ارتكبت على كوكب الأرض.
We're kind of like greedy kids, using it all up, aren't we?
نحن كنوع من الاطفال الجشعين، وذلك باستخدام كل شيء ، أليس كذلك؟
And today is a time for me to talk to you about water.
واليوم حان الوقت بالنسبة لي أن أتحدث إليكم عن المياه.
It's not only because we like to drink lots of it,
انها ليست فقط لأننا نشرب الكثير منها
and its marvelous derivatives, beer, wine, etc.
ومن مشتقاته الرائعة، والبيرة، والنبيذ، إلخ.
And, of course, watch it fall from the sky
وبطبيعة الحال، ونحن نشاهده ينزل من السماء
and flow in our wonderful rivers,
ونتابع جري انهارنا الرائعة
but for several other reasons as well.
ولاسباب اخرى ايضا
When I was a kid, growing up in New York,
عندما كنت طفلا اكبر في مدينة نيويورك
I was smitten by snakes, the same way most kids are
كنت كغيري من الأطفال مغرما بالثعابين
smitten by tops, marbles, cars, trains, cricket balls.
وغيرها مثل، قمم الرخام والسيارات والقطارات كرات الكريكيت.
And my mother, brave lady,
وامي الشجاعة
was partly to blame,
كانت تلومني
taking me to the New York Natural History Museum,
وتاخذني لمتحف التاريخ الطبيعي بنيويورك
buying me books on snakes,
وتشتري لي كتبا عن الثعابين
and then starting this infamous career of mine,
وهذا ما اوحي لي هذه المهنة في رأسي
which has culminated in
والتي تطورت الى
of course, arriving in India 60 years ago,
60 عاما من العمل في الهند
brought by my mother, Doris Norden,
وجلبت امي دوريس نوردن معي
and my stepfather, Rama Chattopadhyaya.
وزوج امي راما كاتوبادايا
It's been a roller coaster ride.
وكان ذلك تحولا حقيقيا
Two animals, two iconic reptiles
اثنين من الحيوانات، واثنين من الزواحف المبدعة
really captivated me very early on.
أثرا فيَّ منذ زمن
One of them was the remarkable gharial.
احدهما تمساح الجارهيل المميز
This crocodile, which grows to almost 20 feet long
هذا التمساح الذي بطول عشرين قدما
in the northern rivers,
في الأنهار الشمالية ،
and this charismatic snake, the king cobra.
وهذا الثعبان الكاريزمي ، الكوبرا الملك.
What my purpose of the talk today really is,
الغرض من حديثي اليوم
is to sort of indelibly scar your minds
هو ان اعيد صياغة عقولكم
with these charismatic and majestic creatures.
حول هذه المخلوقات الكاريزمية والساحرة
Because this is what you will take away from here,
لأن هذا هو ما [آمل] سوف تأخذون بعيدا من هنا،
a reconnection with nature, I hope.
اعادة اتصال مع الطبيعة كما أمل
The king cobra is quite remarkable for several reasons.
الكوبرا الملك رائع جدا لعدة أسباب.
What you're seeing here is very recently shot images
انتم تشاهدون صورا ملتقطة حديثا
in a forest nearby here,
في غابة قريبة من هنا
of a female king cobra making her nest.
لأنثي كوبرا تصنع عشها
Here is a limbless animal, capable of gathering a huge mound of leaves,
هنا هو حيوان ثدي مشوه، وقادر على جر كومة كبيرة من الأوراق،
and then laying her eggs inside,
ثم تضع بيضها تحتها
to withstand 5 to 10 [meters of rainfall],
لتصمد حتي 5-10 أمتار في الغابة المطيرة
in order that the eggs can incubate over the next 90 days,
ويجب أن تحتمل هذه البيضات 90 يوما قادمة
and hatch into little baby king cobras.
وتفقس لتصبح صغار كوبرا
So, she protects her eggs,
لذلك فهي تحمي بيضها
and after three months,
وبعد ثلاثة اشهر
the babies finally do hatch out.
تخرج الصغار من البيض
A majority of them will die, of course. There is very high mortality
معظمها سيموت طبعا . اعلي نسبة للوفيات
in little baby reptiles who are just 10 to 12 inches long.
تكون من الصغار اللواتي يكون طولها 10-12 بوصة
My first experience with king cobras was in '72
اول تجربة لي مع ملك الكوبرا في العام 72
at a magical place called Agumbe,
في مكان ساحر يدعي اجومبي
in Karnataka, this state.
في كاراتانكا هذه الولاية
And it is a marvelous rain forest.
وهي عبارة عن غابة ممطرة ورائعة
This first encounter
اول لقاء
was kind of like the
كان مثل
Maasai boy who kills the lion to become a warrior.
صبي الماساي الذي يقتل الأسد ليصبح محارب.
It really changed my life totally.
حقيقة لقد غير هذا اللقاء حياتي
And it brought me straight into the conservation fray.
وجلبتني مباشرة الي هذا الحديث
I ended up starting this research
انتهى بي الأمر لكي أشرع بهذا البحث
and education station in Agumbe,
ومركز الأبحاث في اجومبي
which you are all of course invited to visit.
والذي بالطبع انتم جميعا مدعوون الى زيارته
This is basically a base wherein
وهي عبارة عن قاعدة
we are trying to gather and learn
نتعلم ونجمع المعلومات فيها
virtually everything about the biodiversity
كل شيء تقريبا عن التنوع البيولوجي
of this incredibly complex forest system,
في هذه الغابة المعقدة تنظيميا
and try to hang on to what's there,
واحاول التعلق بما هو هنا
make sure the water sources are protected and kept clean,
والتاكد من ان مصادر المياه محفوظة ومحمية
and of course, having a good time too.
وبالطبع معايشة وقت جميل
You can almost hear the drums
يمكنك سماع الطبول تقريبا
throbbing back in that little cottage where we stay when we're there.
تخفق في ذلك الكوخ الذي نعيش فيه
It was very important for us to get through to the people.
ومن المهم جدا بالنسبة لنا من خلال الحصول على الناس.
And through the children is usually the way to go.
وذلك من خلال الأطفال
They are fascinated with snakes. They haven't got
وقد كانوا مندهشين بالأفاعي حيث انهم لم يحصلوا
that steely thing that you end up
علي هذا الشي الصلب الذي توصلوا اليه
either fearing or hating or despising or loathing them in some way.
سواء كانوا خائفين او مشمئزين
They are interested.
فقد كانوا مهتمين
And it really works to start with them.
وكانوا هم البداية الجيدة
This gives you an idea of the size of some of these snakes.
هذا يعطيك فكرة عن حجم بعض هذه الثعابين.
This is an average size king cobra, about 12 feet long.
هذا هو متوسط حجم الملك كوبرا، حوالي 12 أقدام
And it actually crawled into somebody's bathroom,
وقد زحف فعلا الى حمام شخص ما،
and was hanging around there for two or three days.
وكان معلقا هناك مابين يومين الي ثلاثة ايام
The people of this part of India
هؤلاء الاشخاص في هذا الجزء من الهند
worship the king cobra.
يقدسون الكوبرا الملك
And they didn't kill it. They called us to catch it.
لكنهم لايقتلونها بل يلاحقوها من اجل قبضها
Now we've caught more than 100 king cobras
وتم قبض اكثر من 100 منها
over the last three years,
في الثلاث سنوات الأخيرة
and relocated them in nearby forests.
وتم اطلاق سراحهم في الغابة
But in order to find out the real secrets of these creatures
ولكن لمعرفة الأسرار الحقيقية لهذه المخلوقات
[it was necessary] for us to actually insert
كان من الضروري لنتعلم ان ...
a small radio transmitter inside [each] snake.
نضع اجهزة رادار مرسله داخل كل ثعبان
Now we are able to follow them and find out their secrets,
واصبحنا نتبعهم ونعرف اسرارهم
where the babies go after they hatch,
واين تذهب الاطفال بعد فقسها
and remarkable things like this you're about to see.
واشياء رائعة انتم على وشك رؤيتها
This was just a few days ago in Agumbe.
هذا قبل ايام قليلة في اجومبي
I had the pleasure of being close to this large king cobra
وكانت تلك متعة ان نلقي نظرة عن قرب عليها
who had caught a venomous pit viper.
وهي تقبض ثعبان ساما
And it does it in such a way that it doesn't get bitten itself.
وفعلت ذلك بطريقة لم تؤذي نفسها
And king cobras feed only on snakes.
وهذا الثعبان يتغذي فقط علي الأفاعي
This [little snake] was kind of a tid-bit for it,
وكان هذا [الثعبان قليلا] نوع من بت الدار من أجلها ،
what we'd call a "vadai" or a donut or something like that.
ومايعرف محليا بالفادني او الدونات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Usually they eat something a bit larger.
عادة هي تاكل شئ اكبر من ذلك
In this case a rather strange and inexplicable
في هذه الحالة كان السلوك غريبا وغير قابل للشرح
activity happened over the last breeding season,
هذا النشاط حدث في موسم التزاوج الماضي
wherein a large male king cobra actually grabbed a female king cobra,
حيث كان هناك ذكر فعليا يمسك بأنثي كوبرا
didn't mate with it, actually killed it and swallowed it.
لم يكونا يتعاشران لكن فعليا قتلها وابتلعها
We're still trying to explain and come to terms with
ومازلنا نعمل علي تفسير ذلك
what is the evolutionary advantage of this.
وماهي الميزة التقدمية لهذا الفعل
But they do also a lot of other remarkable things.
ولكن هنالك ايضا المزيد من الاعمال المدهشة
This is again, something [we were able to see] by virtue of the fact
وهذا شيء جديد، [كنا قادرين على رؤية] بحكم الواقع...
that we had a radio transmitter in one of the snakes.
لأنه كان لدينا جهاز لاسلكي في واحدة من الثعابين،
This male snake, 12 feet long, met another male king cobra.
ذكر هذا الثعبان، 12 أقدام التقى ملك كوبرا ذكر آخر.
And they did this incredible ritual combat dance.
وفعلوا هذا الفعل غير القابل للتصديق من طقوس الرقص.
It's very much like the rutting of mammals, including humans,
انه يشبه كثيرا الانس بين الثدييات، بما في ذلك البشر،
you know, sorting out our differences, but gentler, no biting allowed.
تعلمون، نوع من العراك، ولكن ألطف، والعض غير مسموح به
It's just a wresting match,
فقط مباراة للمصارعة
but a remarkable activity.
لكن نشاط مدهش
Now, what are we doing with all this information?
الان ماذا نفعل بهذه المعلومة؟
What's the point of all this?
ما النقطة من هذا كله
Well, the king cobra is literally
هو ان الكوبرا الملك هو كذلك حرفيا
a keystone species in these rainforests.
للأنواع الرئيسية في الغابات المطيرة.
And our job is to convince the authorities
ومهمتنا هي لإقناع السلطات
that these forests have to be protected.
أن هذه الغابات يجب أن تكون محمية.
And this is one of the ways we do it,
وهذه هي واحدة من الطرق التي تمكننا من ..
by learning as much as we can
التعلم قدر المستطاع
about something so remarkable and so iconic in the rainforests there,
عن شيء رائع جدا ومبدع حتى في الغابات المطيرة هناك،
in order to help protect trees, animals
لتتم حماية الأشجار والحيوانات
and of course the water sources.
وبالتاكيد مصادر المياه
You've all heard, perhaps, of Project Tiger
قد تكونون سمعتم بمشروع النمر
which started back in the early '70s,
الذي بدا في بداية السبعينات
which was, in fact, a very dynamic time for conservation.
والذي كانت حقيقة فترة مرنة للحديث
We were piloted, I could say,
لقد كنا نغلي ... ان امكنني القول
by a highly autocratic stateswoman,
من إمرأة دولة استبدادية للغاية ،
but who also had an incredible passion for environment.
وفي نفس الوقت لديها شغف رائع حول البيئة
And this is the time when Project Tiger emerged.
وفي ذلك الوقت كانت بداية المشروع
And, just like Project Tiger,
وفعلا احببت مشروع النمر
our activities with the king cobra
ونشاطنا مع الكوبرا الملك
is to look at a species of animal
وكان التركيز على نوع من الحيوانات
so that we protect its habitat and everything within it.
حتى يتسنى لنا حماية بيئتها وكل شيء في داخلها.
So, the tiger is the icon.
لذا كان النمر هو الرمز
And now the king cobra is a new one.
والأن الكوبرا الملك
All the major rivers in south India
في انهار جنوب الهند
are sourced in the Western Ghats,
ومصدرها في غرب القاتس
the chain of hills running along the west coast of India.
سلسلة من التلال على طول الساحل الغربي للهند.
It pours out millions of gallons every hour,
انه يصب بها ملايين الجالونات في كل ساعة،
and supplies drinking water to at least 300 million people,
وإمدادات المياه الصالحة للشرب ما لا يقل عن 300 مليون شخص،
and washes many, many babies,
ويغسل العديد والعديد من الأطفال،
and of course feeds many, many animals,
وبالطبع يغذي حيوانات كثيرة،
both domestic and wild,
الأليفة منها والمتوحشة
produces thousands of tons of rice.
ويورد الاف الأطنان من الأرز
And what do we do? How do we respond to this?
وماذا نفعل؟ كيف نرد على هذا؟
Well, basically, we dam it, we pollute it,
حسنا ، في الأساس ، نسده ونلوثه
we pour in pesticides, weedicides, fungicides.
ونلوثه بالفطريات والميبدات والسموم
You drink it in peril of your life.
وانت تشرب هذا الخطر
And the thing is, it's not just big industry.
والشيء هو، انها ليست مجرد صناعة كبيرة.
It's not misguided river engineers
وليست هندسة انهار مبدعة
who are doing all this; it's us.
وليس من يقوم بها قوم مبدعون انه نحن
It seems that our citizens find the best way to dispose of garbage
علي مايبدو ان مدننا وجدت الطرق المثلي للتخلص من الأوساخ
are in water sources.
في موارد المياه
Okay. Now we're going north, very far north.
الأن سوف نتوجه الي اقصى الشمال
North central India, the Chambal River
في وسط الهند ونهر الجامبل
is where we have our base.
حيث تكون هنالك قاعدتنا
This is the home of the gharial, this incredible crocodile.
حيث منزل تمساح الجاريال الرائع
It is an animal which has been on the Earth
وهو حيوان كان على ظهر الأرض منذ
for just about 100 million years.
100 مليون عام
It survived even during the time that the dinosaurs died off.
نجا وحتى خلال الوقت الذي ماتت فيه الديناصورات.
It has remarkable features.
بسبب ميزاته الرائعة
Even though it grows to 20 feet long,
رغم طوله ذي ال 20 قدما
since it eats only fish it's not dangerous to human beings.
وبما انه يأكل الأسماك فقط فانه لا يشكل خطرا علي البشر
It does have big teeth, however,
لكن لديه فم كبير
and it's kind of hard to convince people
وانها نوع من الصعب إقناع الناس
if an animal has big teeth, that it's a harmless creature.
إذا حيوان له اسنان كبيرة، انه مخلوق غير مؤذي.
But we, actually, back in the early '70s,
ولكننا وفي الواقع وبالعودة الي العام 70
did surveys,
قمنا بأبحاث
and found that gharial were extremely rare.
ووجدنا ان الجاريال كان نادرا جدا
In fact, if you see the map,
في الحقيقة وكما نرى في الخريطة
the range of their original habitat
كان نطاقه ونشاطه يمتد
was all the way from the Indus in Pakistan
من الاندس في باكستان
to the Irrawaddy in Burma.
الي ارادوي في بومباي
And now it's just limited to a couple of spots
اما الأن فهو محدد في نقاط محددة
in Nepal and India.
في نيبال والهند
So, in fact at this point
لذلك في الحقيقة
there are only 200 breeding gharial left in the wild.
هناك فقط 200 جاريال في البرية
So, starting in the mid-'70s
لذلك من بداية ال 70
when conservation was at the fore,
عندما كان الحفظ في الصدارة،
we were actually able to start projects which were
تمكنا من بدء مشارع وهي
basically government supported
بدعم من الحكومة
to collect eggs from the wild from the few remaining nests
لجمع البيض من البرية من الاعشاش القليلة المتبقية
and release 5,000 baby gharial
والافراج عن 5000 طفل جاريال
back to the wild.
لكي تعود الى البرية
And pretty soon we were seeing sights like this.
وقريبا جدا ونحن نرى مشاهد من هذا القبيل.
I mean, just incredible to see bunches of gharial
منظر رائع من مجموعات الجاريال
basking on the river again.
تعوم في النهر وترسو مجددا
But complacency does have a tendency to breed contempt.
لكن الرضا عن الذات لديه ميل لتولد الاحتقار.
And, sure enough, with all the other pressures on the river,
والمؤكد، مع وجود جميع الضغوط الأخرى على النهر ،
like sand mining, for example,
مثل استخراج الرمال، على سبيل المثال،
very, very heavy cultivation all the way down to the river's edge,
والزراعة المكثفة جدا على طول الطريق إلى حافة النهر،
not allowing the animals to breed anymore,
لم تعد تسمح للحيوانات بالتوالد بعد الآن،
we're looking at
نحن نبحث في
even more problems building up for the gharial,
مشاكل اخري تواجه القاريال
despite the early good intentions.
على الرغم من النوايا الطيبة في وقت مبكر.
Their nests hatching along the riverside
وفقست اعشاشها علي جانبي النهر
producing hundreds of hatchlings. It's just an amazing sight.
واخرجت المئات منها في منظر هائل
This was actually just taken last year.
اخذت هذه الصورة العام الماضي
But then the monsoon arrives,
ولكن بعد ذلك وصول الامطار الموسمية،
and unfortunately downriver there is always a dam or
لسوء الحظ كانت هنالك السدود
there is always a barrage,
وهناك دائما سد
and, shoop, they get washed down to their doom.
مما يؤدي الى تخريب البيئات في الانهار
Luckily there is still a lot of interest.
لحسن الحظ لا يزال هناك الكثير من الاهتمام.
My pals in the Crocodile Specialist Group of the IUCN,
الزملاء في الفريق المتخصص للتمساح في الطبيعة،
the [Madras Crocodile Bank], an NGO,
بنك مادرس للتماسيح و ان جي او
the World Wildlife Fund,
كمُمَول عالمي
the Wildlife Institute of India, State Forest Departments,
والمعهد الهندي للحياة البرية قسم الغابات الاستوئية
and the Ministry of Environment, we all work together on stuff.
ووزارة البيئة، وعملنا كلنا على أشياء
But it's possibly, and definitely not enough.
لكن فعليا لم يكن ذلك كافيا
For example, in the winter of 2007 and 2008,
على سبيل المثال ، في شتاء 2007 و 2008،
there was this incredible die-off of gharial, in the Chambal River.
كان هذا الموت المفجع للجاريال في نهر الجابال
Suddenly dozens of gharial appearing on the river, dead.
فجأة ظهر علي السطع الألاف من تماسيح الججاريال المتوفية
Why? How could it happen?
لماذا وكيف حدث هذا؟
This is a relatively clean river.
هذا تقريبا نهر نقي
The Chambal, if you look at it, has clear water.
نهر الجامبل لو نظرت اليه لديه مياه نقية
People scoop water out of the Chambal and drink it,
الناس يشربون من هذا النهر
something you wouldn't do in most north Indian rivers.
شي لايفعل غالبا مع انهار شمال الهند
So, in order to try to find out the answer to this,
لذلك لمعرفة الجواب
we got veterinarians from all over the world
وصلنا من الأطباء البيطريين في جميع أنحاء العالم
working with Indian vets to try to figure out what was happening.
العمل مع الاطباء البيطريون الهندييون لمحاولة معرفة ما كان يحدث.
I was there for a lot of the necropsies on the riverside.
وكان هنالك الكثير علي جانبي النهر
And we actually looked through
وعبره
all their organs and tried to figure out what was going on.
وفتح جميع اعضائها للوصول الي حقيقة مايحدث
And it came down to something called gout,
وانه جاء الى شيء يسمى النقرس،
which, as a result of kidney breakdown
التي، تأتي نتيجة لانهيار الكلى
is actually uric acid crystals throughout the body,
فقد وجد بلورات حمض اليوريك منشترة في جميع اجزاء الجسم
and worse in the joints,
والأسوء انه وجد في المفاصل،
which made the gharial unable to swim.
مما يجعل التمساح غير قادر علي السباحة
And it's a horribly painful death.
وهذا حقيقة موت مؤلم
Just downriver from the Chambal is the
في اسفل النهر
filthy Yamuna river, the sacred Yamuna river.
نهر يامونا ونهر يامونا المقدس.
And I hate to be so ironic and sarcastic about it
وأنا أكره أن تكون المفارقة الساخرة حول هذا الموضوع
but it's the truth. It's just one of the filthiest cesspools you can imagine.
لكنها الحقيقة. انها مجرد واحدة من أقذر البالوعات يمكنك أن تتخيله.
It flows down through Delhi, Mathura, Agra,
إذا كان يتدفق من خلال أنهار دلهي، ماثورا، اجرا،
and gets just about every bit of effluent you can imagine.
جارفا معه كل ذرة من النفايات السائلة يمكنك أن تتخيلها
So, it seemed that the toxin that was killing the gharial
لذا، يبدو أنه السم الذي قتل الجاريال
was something in the food chain,
كان شيئا في السلسلة الغذائية،
something in the fish they were eating.
شيء ما في السمك الذي يأكلونه.
And, you know, once a toxin is in the food chain
وكما تعلمون، دخول السم مرة واحدة في السلسلة الغذائية
everything is affected, including us.
يؤثر علي بقية السلسلة
Because these rivers are the lifeblood of people all along their course.
لأن هذه الأنهار هي شريان الحياة لجميع الناس على طول مسارها.
In order to try to answer some of these questions,
في محاولة للرد على بعض هذه الأسئلة
we again turn to technology,
لننتقل مرة أخرى إلى التكنولوجيا
to biological technology, in this case,
الى التكنولوجيا البيولوجية ، وفي هذه الحالة ،
again, telemetry, putting radios on 10 gharial,
مرة أخرى، وعلى القياس، وضعت أشرطة الفيديو على 10 من تماسيح الجاريال
and actually following their movements. They're being watched
وفعلا تبعنا تحركاتهم. ووضعناهم تحت المراقبة
everyday as we speak, to try to find out
كل يوم ونحن نتكلم، في محاولة لمعرفة
what this mysterious toxin is.
ما هذا السم الغامض.
The Chambal river is an absolutely incredible place.
نهر الجامبال هو المكان لا يصدق على الاطلاق.
It's a place that's famous to a lot of you who know
انه المكان الشهير والكثير منكم يعرفون ذلك
about the bandits, the dacoits
حول قطاع الطرق، واللصوص
who used to work up there. And there still are quite a few around.
الذين استخدموا للعمل هناك. ولا يزال هناك عدد غير قليل من حولها.
But Poolan Devi was one [of them]. Which actually Shekhar Kapur
لكن بولان ديفي كان منهم، الذي كان فعلا شيخار كابور
made an incredible movie, "The Bandit Queen," which I urge you to see.
الفيلم الذي لا يصدق و، ملكة اللصوص، وأنا أحثكم على رؤيته.
You'll get to see the incredible [Chambal] landscape as well.
سوف تحصل على رؤية المشهد لا يصدق عن الجامبال كذلك.
But, again, heavy fishing pressures.
ولكن، مرة أخرى ، وضغوط الصيد الثقيلة.
This is one of the last repositories of the
هذا هو واحد من المستودعات الأخيرة من
Ganges river dolphin,
دلفين نهر الغانج،
various species of turtles,
مختلف الأنواع من السلاحف،
thousands of migratory birds,
والآلاف من الطيور المهاجرة،
and fishing is causing problems like this.
وصيد الأسماك يسبب مشاكل من هذا القبيل.
And now [these] new elements of human intolerance
والآن [هذه] عناصر جديدة من تعصب الإنسان
for river creatures like the gharial
لمخلوقات النهر وهي الجاريال
means that if they don't drown in the net,
يعني أنه إذا لم يغرق في الشباك،
then they simply cut their beaks off.
ثم قطعوا ببساطة مناقيرها
Animals like the Ganges river dolphin
الحيوانات مثل دولفين نهر الغانج
which is just down to a few left,
والذي يقطن الى الشمال قليلا
and it is also critically endangered.
وكما أنها معرضة للخطر.
So, who is next? Us?
لذا، من التالي؟ نحن؟
Because we are all dependent on these water sources.
لأننا جميعا نعتمد على هذه المصادر المائية.
So, we all know about the Narmada river,
بذلك ، نحن كلنا نعرف كل شيء عن نهر نارمادا،
the tragedies of dams, the tragedies of huge projects
مآسي السدود ومآسي مشاريع ضخمة
which displace people and wreck river systems
الذي أدى إلى تشريد الناس وتحطيم نظام النهر
without providing livelihoods.
دون توفير سبل العيش.
And development just basically going berserk,
ان التنمية تهدف في الاساس
for a double figure growth index, basically.
لمضاعفة نسبة الناتج المحلي
So, we're not sure where this story is going to end,
وبذلك ، نحن لسنا متأكدين أين سنصل بعد هذا سواء كان يعني هذا
whether it's got a happy or sad ending.
الوصول للنهاية السعيدة او الحزينة في النهاية
And climate change is certainly going
وتغير المناخ بالتأكيد
to turn all of our theories and predictions on their heads.
سوف ينقلب ضدنا في فترة ما
We're still working hard at it.
ونحن لا نزال نعمل بجهد فيه.
We've got a lot of a good team of people working up there.
لدينا الكثير من الفرق الجيدة من الناس الذين يعملون هناك.
And the thing is, you know, the decision makers,
و كما تعلمون، فإن صناع القرار يصنعون
the folks in power,
الناس في السلطة،
they're up in their bungalows and so on in Delhi,
انهم في طوابقهم العليا وهلم جرا في دلهي،
in the city capitals. They are all supplied with plenty of water. It's cool.
في عواصم المدن. التي يتم توفيرها جميعا مع الكثير من الماء. انها جميلة.
But out on the rivers there are still millions of people
ولكن من على طرفي الانهار .. مازال هناك الملايين من الناس
who are in really bad shape.
الذين هم في حالة سيئة حقا.
And it's a bleak future for them.
وان المستقبل قاتم بالنسبة لهم.
So, we have our Ganges and Yamuna cleanup project.
لذا، لدينا الغانج ويامونا ينظمون المشروع.
We've spent hundreds of millions of dollars on it,
لقد قضينا مئات الملايين من الدولارات على ذلك،
and nothing to show for it. Incredible.
ولم يظهر منه شي مذهل
So, people talk about political will.
هكذا، يتحدث الناس عن الإرادة السياسية.
During the die-off of the gharial we did galvanize a lot of action.
حينما تموت الجاريال نفعل الكثير من العمل.
Government cut through all the red tape,
والحكومة تتحفز وتقطع الشريط الأحمر
we got foreign vets on it. It was great.
حصلنا على الاطباء البيطريون من الخارج وكان ذلك عظيما
So, we can do it.
اجل يمكننا فعل ذلك
But if you stroll down to the Yamuna
ولكن إذا كنت في نزهة وصولا الى يامونا
or to the Gomati in Lucknow,
في جاموتي في لوشناو
or to the Adyar river in Chennai,
أو إلى النهر الديار في شيناي،
or the Mula-Mutha river in Pune,
أو نهر مولا - مؤتة في بيون،
just see what we're capable of doing to a river. It's sad.
انظر فقط ما نحن قادرون على القيام به للنهر. انه لامر محزن.
But I think the final note really is
لكني اعتقد كملاحظة أخيرة حقا
that we can do it.
يمكننا أن نفعل ذلك.
The corporates, the artists, the wildlife nuts,
والشركات، والفنانين، ومجانين والحياة البرية ،
the good old everyday folks
مثل ايام البشرية الخوالي
can actually bring these rivers back.
يمكننا اعادة هذا النهر الي سابق عهده
And the final word is
واخر كلمة هي
that there is a king cobra looking over our shoulders.
أن هناك أكثر من الكوبرا الملك علي عاتقنا
And there is a gharial looking at us from the river.
والجارريال من النهر
And these are powerful water totems.
وهذه امواج نهر جامحة
And they are going to disturb our dreams until we do the right thing.
وأنهم ذاهبون إلى زعزعة أحلامك حتى نفعل الشيء الصحيح.
Namaste.
نامسكار
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thanks, Rom. Thanks a lot.
كريس اندرسون:شكرا روم.شكرا جزيلا
You know, most people are terrified of snakes.
انت تعلم ان الكثيرين مرعوبون من الثعابين
And there might be quite a few people here who would be
وربما يكون هناك قليل من الناس الذين سيكونون هنا
very glad to see the last king cobra bite the dust.
مسرور جدا لرؤية الملك كوبرا ينفض الغبار عن نفسه
Do you have those conversations with people?
هل لديك تلك المحادثات مع الناس؟
How do you really get them to care?
كيف تحصل حقا لهم الرعاية؟
Romulus Whitaker: I take the sort of humble approach,
راموس وايتاكر: : أغتنم هذا النوع من النهج المتواضع
I guess you could say. I don't say that snakes are huggable exactly.
انا لا أقول انها حيوانات ودودة وقابله للعناق
It's not like the teddy bear.
ليست مثل دب الألعاب
But I sort of -- there is an innocence in these animals.
لكنني نوع من ال -- هناك براءة في هذه الحيوانات.
And when the average person looks at a cobra
وعندم ينظر الشخص العادي إلى كوبرا
going "Ssssss!" like that, they say, "My god,
وهي تفحفح "سسسسس" يقول ياإلهي
look at that angry, dangerous creature."
نظرة على مخلوق شديد الغضب. "
I look at it as a creature who is totally frightened
وانا انظر اليها علي انها هي الخائفة من
of something so dangerous as a human being.
شئ خطر كالإنسان
And that is the truth. And that's what I try to get out.
وهذه هي الحقيقة. وهذا ما أحاول الخروج به.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: Now, incredible footage you showed of the viper being killed.
سي اي: الآن، لقطات مرعبة أظهرت لكم مايجري من قتل الافعى.
You were saying that that hasn't been filmed before.
وتقولون أن ذلك لم يتم تصويرها من قبل.
RW: Yes, this is actually the first time anyone of us knew about it, for one thing.
ار إم:اول مرة يعرف شخص عن هذا
As I said, it's just like a little snack for him, you know?
كما قلت، انها مجرد وجبة خفيفة من كثير لم يعرض
Usually they eat larger snakes like rat snakes,
وعادة ما يأكلون الثعابين الكبيرة مثل الثعابين الفئران،
or even cobras.
او حتي الكوبرا نفسها
But this guy who we're following right now is in the deep jungle.
ولكن هذا الرجل الذي نحن نتبعه في اعماق الغابة
Whereas other king cobras
حيث تلك الأفاعي
very often come into the human interface,
وغالبا ما تأتي في واجهة الإنسان،
you know, the plantations, to find big rat snakes and stuff.
وكما تعرفون في المزارع حيث تبحث عن الفئران الكبيرة
This guy specializes in pit vipers.
هذا الرجل متخصص في حفرة الافاعي.
And the guy who is working there with them,
والرجل الذي يعمل هناك معهم،
he's from Maharashtra, he said, "I think he's after the nusha."
وقال انه من ولاية ماهاراشترا، وقال "اعتقد انه من النوشا".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, the nusha means the high.
ونوشا تعني الإرتفاع
Whenever he eats the pit viper he gets this little venom rush.
حيث انه ينتشي كلما تعضه افعي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: Thanks Rom. Thank you.
سي اي: شكرا لك
(Applause)
(تصفيق)